James Dwight Dana Archives
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
James Dwight Dana Archives
1830-1895
IZAR.001614
Yale Peabody Museum of Natural History
10
various boxes
Archives of James Dana, mostly dealing with invertebrate zoology.
Dana, James Dwight, 1813-1895
Biographical Sketch
In terms of enduring scientific achievement, James Dwight Dana (b. 1813, d. 1895) is one of Yale's most notable scientific figures. His contributions to geology, mineralogy and zoology are the basis of classification systems still in use today by scientists in these fields. Dana was educated at Yale, where he received scientific training fromBenjamin Silliman, the prominent scientist and founder of The American Journal of Science.
In 1836, Dana was invited to be a scientific participant of the United States Exploring Expedition, due to sail to the South Seas in 1838. Originally invited on the expedition as its geologist, Dana assumed the role of zoologist after the departure of James Couthouy in 1840. Dana produced 2 important monographs based on his study of animals collected by the expedition. These monographs, one on corals and anemones and the other on crustaceans, were extraordinary for their sheer size, scope and detail. Virtually no modern coral or crustacean researcher today can undertake significant systematic research without encountering the legacy left by James Dana.
Description of the Material
The archives of J.D. Dana notably include field notes from his time on the U.S. Exploring Expedition.
New York; Connecticut; Hawaii; Yale Peabody Museum; Yale University
- U.S. Exploring Expedition, 1838-1842; Series I
  Scope and Contents
  James Dana archives relating to his time during the U.S. Exploring Expedition.
  - Field Notes. Field notes from the U.S. Exploring Expedition., 1838-1842; 001616
    - Field Notes. Figures and description of "animalcula" observed during the U.S. Exploring Expedition., 1838-1842; 001617
  - Figures, Illustrations, etc. Figures, illustrations, etc. used in publications or for research purposes., 1842-1855; 005903
    - Zoophytes, Plate 36. Proof of Plate 36, Zoophytes., 005904
    - Zoophytes; Plate 36, Figure 2. Pencil sketch of Figure 2, plate 36, Zoophytes., 005905
  - Publications. Physical copies of publications on the Exploring Expedition., 1842-1855; 005902
    - Zoophytes. Zoophytes, U. S. Exploring Expedition, Atlas, text, 1852; 000001
    - Zoophytes. Zoophytes, U. S. Exploring Expedition, Atlas, plates 1-61., 1852; 000002
- Research Materials, 1833-1895; Series II
  James Dana research materials.
  - Reference Material. Annotated refernce material., 1833-1895; 001627
    - Reference Material. A collection of reprints on Crustacea. There are annotations by Dana., Apr 1851; 001628